if you look at most of the trade
examples that are given in trading
lessons you'll notice that people are
usually showing off these opportunities
that lead to huge profitable moves
because obviously they look more
impressive and it makes them look like
they're a better Trader but this means
that when you start trading you feel
like you should be looking for the same
but smaller profits and shortterm moves
can have a place in your trading as well
as long as they fulfill important
criteria and I'm going to show you what
I mean throughout this video by walking
you through a trade example that was
taken during the US election week but
first what are these important criteria
so let's think about what leads to
successful trading from a trade point of
view not trading psychology or routines
or anything but from a trade point of
view so we have the trade quality and
the trade quantity quality can be
measured by the expectancy of the trade
this basically means that if you took
the same type of trade over and over
again when you calculate the times it
loses and the times it profits and sort
of combine them what's the overall
contribution to your return so the
higher the expectancy of a trade the
more it's going to contribute your
returns in a positive way and if the
expectancy is negative it's going to
contribute in a negative way because
it's going to lead you to losses over
the long term now if you want to
understand this further and start
applying it to your trades check out the
link in the description box to my free
training that will walk you through this
process I personally believe it's the
most important 1hour training that any
Trader can go through but especially if
you're relatively new to trading then we
have the trade quantity so if the trade
has a positive expectancy the more often
you take those sorts of Trades the more
profitable you're going to be over the
long term because each trade it's almost
like a snowflake like lots of these
little snowflakes from these individual
uh positive expectancy trades and it's
the accumulation of them that builds
something more significant a snowman so
in an Ideal World you'd have trades with
the highest possible quality that happen
really frequently so high quality High
quantity but that's not usually the case
instead there's usually some sort of
tradeoff that takes place because the
higher expectancy trades will usually be
these bigger Market moves that take a
while to play out and happen less
frequently you know you're not going to
find huge opportunities every hour so
they're less frequent they take a while
to play out whereas the trades that
happen more frequently that sort of
happen quicker are going to be lower
expectancy because there smaller Market
moves therefore we can think of all
possible trades falling somewhere on
this chart and if you want to get the
best performance from your trading you
should be looking for trades that fall
into either of these areas because if
the trade Falls in this area you're
spending time on opportunities that
contribute less to your success than
other opportunities would so you'd be
better off going out and finding
different sorts of opportunities rather
than wasting your time Capital mental
energy on those sorts of opportunities
and this is exactly how I break down my
trading I focus on finding two
categories of Trades either it's going
to be these big runaway opportunities
that come less frequently or it's going
to be what I call my bread and butter
trades which are these short-term
positive expectancy ones and today we're
going to be focusing on that category so
positive expectancy trades that are
quick so don't take much management of
the trades and they're frequent they
happen more often but this doesn't mean
that I'm just looking for General
scalping in fact I hate the term
scalping I think it's quite misleading
instead I'm looking for a very specific
type of situation A Dependable range the
benefit of a range is that you'll often
get more than one opportunity from a
single range which means once you've
done your analysis it's not just looking
for one entry and then either it's a
profit or a loss but you'll often get
more entries from that one piece of
analysis so more bang for your buck
they're Dependable which means that my
probability estimates will be more
accurate than other situations they're
they're so shortterm so it doesn't take
long to be in and out of the trade and
they're relatively easy to manage which
means it takes less mental effort so
it's really like an ideal situation now
my trading approach starts with a market
selection process and I always encourage
everyone to follow a market selection
process because great trades begin with
great markets so Market selection is
basically a set of analysis steps that I
can do very quickly which allows me to
scan through a lot of different markets
really efficiently to identify which one
is the right one to focus on because
let's face it doing full analysis on a
market takes time and it takes effort so
I want to make sure that the market I'm
focused on and I'm doing that full
analysis for is worth spending that much
time on if you spend too much of your
trading session analyzing this bunch of
different markets you'll miss
opportunities and when you do have an
opportunity you would have already used
a lot of mental energy and you should be
saving that mental energy for when you
need it the most which is is when you're
entering a trade and managing that trade
not wasting it on fruitless analysis so
in this case for Market selection since
it was the US election week if I wanted
to trade a range I needed to wait until
the conclusion of the election when we
knew who was going to be president and
it needed to be a market that wouldn't
be directly impacted by the Federal
Reserve monetary policy decision that
was coming up shortly after so I was
scanning for a market as efficiently as
possible that fulfilled those criteria
while also showing consolidation on
higher time frames ideally with a strong
path of resistance on one side of the
consolidation and I'll explain why
that's important in just a moment so
this led me to Euro Swiss frank which
fulfilled all of those criteria and seem
to be worth doing further analysis on we
could see the consolidation here on the
weekly chart now a lot of Traders avoid
markets like this that are consolidating
because they don't think the conditions
are good for trading since they're
looking for these huge runaway
opportunities but but when I look at
this I know it's in a range or a value
area and could give frequent High
dependability setups then if we look at
the daily chart we can see this path of
resistance that the consolidation is
happening at and it's happening just
below it so this gives me a directional
bias which basically means that I'll be
looking to trade short from the upper
side of the range and there are two
reasons for this firstly it means the
probability of a reversal at the top of
the range is higher than the probability
of a reversal at the bottom of the range
because of that stronger path resistance
from a dominant time frame and secondly
it means there's a higher chance of a
breakout at the bottom and therefore a
further move which would then mean that
I've turned a short-term trade if I've
taken a short from the top of the range
into an even more profitable move if it
ends up being a runaway trade so I'm
looking for a range trade but if it
develops into a bigger long-term move
that's only going to serve me better now
whenever I'm analyzing a market the most
important thing is to understand the
context a lot of Traders just try to
identify setups looking for situations
that meet this list of criteria that
they've got but a setup is just for
timing the entry it's letting you know
now is the right time to enter because
of some shift in activity but the
opportunity itself comes from the
context so the first thing I want to do
is understand what's happened so far
starting with the structure now looking
at the structure on the daily chart we
can see that we had a long-term bearish
Trend with sharp legs down followed by
Deep pullbacks once the trend corrected
the entire previous move so the previous
Trends we struggled to create a new low
and we entered into this sort of
consolidation so breaking this level
would have been an early indication of a
shift to a more bullish situation
because it would be showing us that the
underlying dynamics of the market have
changed whereas failing there would show
that the underlying Dynamics are still
bearish a good way to think about this
is to imagine it's like a shop that's
increasing or reducing its price and
seeing how that affects supply and
demand so if previously the shop was
able to raise prices up here and demand
was still coming in you know the price
was able to go higher and higher but now
even at a lower price there isn't the
same demand it tells us something about
the state of the market about demand
where demand's coming in or not now
obviously in the actual markets it's all
about volume and liquidity so it's a bit
more complex than that shop example but
I always think thinking about the shop
raising and lowering prices it's just a
good way to visualize it and to
understand why structure is important so
since the pric has failed at this level
as a type three close it was clear that
we have a strong path of resistance that
was limiting any bullish activity and
the underlying Dynamics in the market
were still not bullish yet they weren't
necessarily bearish but they're not
bullish yet now I know that maybe
already that sounds like a lot but this
whole process that we've gone through so
far usually just takes me a couple of
minutes maybe even less sometimes when
I'm not having to EXP explain out loud
what I'm doing and why like I'm doing
for you now so don't worry it is really
straightforward so the market selection
process is complete at this point I've
identified this is the market that I
want to focus on so now I'll drop down
in time frames to see what's really
going on within that consolidation and
ideally I'm looking for a range rather
than just a standard sideways market and
I differentiate a range as being a
sideways Market with very clear and
dependable upper and lower boundaries
rather than a usual sideways Market
where the highs and lows are more mixed
but it's just not progressing into a
trend so dropping to the 4-Hour time
frame we can see a range within a range
within a range in other words there are
ranges across different structural time
Horizons so it's a bit like a Russian
doll and these situations are ideal for
short-term trades because it means you
can structure a trade on the shorttime
horizon which means tighter risk but
then be able to restructure the trade
after an initial profitable move to
benefit from the longer term time
Horizons as well and that's perfect
because it means tight risk with
potentially huge upside now there are
three main categories of elements that
I'm analyzing to understand the context
of a market the first one which I've
already mentioned is the structure then
we have the paths of resistance and the
micro structure also known in the dwma
method as the Triad of price action and
if you want me to explain the importance
of each of these elements and how they
contribute to understanding the context
let me know in the comment section down
below if enough people comment I'll do a
video explaining all of it for you so I
added the level here where we can see a
clearly defined top of the range if we
look at the short-term structure we had
low conviction bullish structure that
then failed to create a new high and
went on to break lower which then meant
that there was weakness in the structure
at the time of analyzing this we were
now back at the top testing that high so
it would need to break this level to
return to bullish structure but since we
know we have another path of resistance
from the dominant time frames like I
mentioned earlier it was telling us that
the probabilities would be better than
the base rid for a move back down and
then either staying in sideways
structure or breaking into bearish
structure and when I say the base rate I
mean the probabilities of a situation if
we had no Edge so a oneto one risk
reward situation would have a base rate
of 50% for each outcome a 1 to three
situation would be 25% and 75% the
outcomes and so on so as Traders we can
only make money if the probabilities are
different to the base rate if they're
just at the base rate you're going to be
at break even all the time over time and
probably losing money because of the
transaction costs so my working time
frame for this trade meaning the time
frame that I'm going to look for an
entry on and I'm going to manage the
trade based on was the 1 hour time frame
and here we can see that the market put
in a lot of work at this level before
eventually breaking with momentum
so that means there's likely to be a
buildup of activity there which means
it's a significant level a path of
resistance because that's basically what
a significant level is it's a level or
an area on the chart where we're
expecting a shift in activity and shifts
in activity often happen because of
previous activity so this level went on
to become the bottom of the range which
added more confirmation to its
importance and all of this period here
was the disruption from the US election
now sometimes this sort of activity can
be a bit like a reset for the price
structure that we've developed up until
that point but in this case we can see
that after all of that disruption the
price continued to respect the upper and
lower boundaries of the range so this
was still the value area for the price
therefore if the price is approaching
the top we know there's a chance for
responsive action and that's what we're
keeping an eye out for now on the
morning of election day we had a few
hours of consolidation before we had a
sudden break with strong momentum so
this indicat that there's a possible
demand area there which was then
confirmed by the later interactions so
for me this is going to Mark the bottom
of the range it's not you know precise
but since we have a path of resistance
there around the bottom of the range it
makes sense to use that significant
level as the guide for where the bottom
of the range is so now we have a good
understanding of the context of this
market and the different forces at play
this allows us to anticipate the
potential outcomes estimate the
probabilities of those outcomes and
therefore determine whether or not
there's a viable trade opportunity but
to enter a trade we also need to get the
timing exactly right and with the dwma
method we're focused on Precision so
let's move on to the entry so you can
see how I do that in this situation
there were two time Horizons that play
relative to this time frame the medium
term was in bearish structure a break
Above This level would signal weakness
in the structure but if that level held
we'd still be overall bearish so this
gives me two key levels the first is for
the break in structure which is this
level and the second is the start of
that Trend which also happens to be the
top of the range now usually I'd assess
the structure characteristics that's the
speed length and depth of pullbacks but
with the disruption from the election
the short-term structure is a bit
distorted so any conclusions from the
characteristics would be unreliable so
it's not worth sort of analyzing that
aspect but with the shter term structure
we put in a higher low and then broke
this to enter into bullish structure and
when that happens we want to anticipate
where the end of that wave may come in
where is that level where we're going to
maybe see a shift in activity that will
cause that wave to come to an end not
necessarily to be the terminal point in
that Trend but at least for that wave to
come to an end and in this case we could
do that with a Fibonacci range that had
a perfectly confirmed C Point giving us
a 16 1.8 towards the top of the range
that's what we call an invisible level
and then combined with that we have the
visible level of the top of the range so
it's an invisible level because it's a
projection based on previous movements
now looking at the micro structure the
Triad of price action so the trend
momentum and volume of the recent moves
I had to be cautious about this surging
momentum that was moving towards that
level which indicated herd activity and
we only want to trade when there's
steady state activity but the signs were
showing that we've probably returned
steady state activity and a quick look
at the volume on the volume profile
shows that we were previously seeing
responsive action in this area we can
maybe expect the same now these
interactions were single confirmations
but that still wasn't enough to enter a
trade in this situation we needed a
double confirmation which we got a short
while after with this candle here in
fact it was a triple confirmation so we
had a type three on the previous lower
high showing failure at the level but
without Precision we had a type three on
the 61.8 again showing failure but not
Precision then we had a type one failure
at the top of the range which is an
indication of precision as well as
obviously being failure now along with
this we also already had confirmations
on the 4H hour and the daily time frames
although arguably the 4-Hour
confirmation was just the same as the 1H
hour cuz there were similar levels so
the potential outcomes here were simple
for the first order outcomes we could
either break out of the top of the range
and therefore change the context of the
market or would fail here and return to
the B point of the confirmed Fibonacci
range which is my TMP level trade move
potential level I won't explain what TMP
is in this video but you can basically
think of this point as being the first
decision point so it's not a profit
Target it's a decision point so we can
now think about what these potential
outcomes will mean for the context of
the market and this is essentially how
we structure and plan our trade
opportunity so if this first order
outcome of breaking the top of the range
did happen then the probability of
profitable outcomes would have fallen
enough to no longer make the opportunity
viable for a trade expectancy point of
view because then the paths of
resistance were on the wrong side of the
price and it's also showing that we've
broken out of the range maybe switching
into bullish structure and so on so with
that in mind to protect against the
negative first order outcome my stop
loss would be above these Wicks here so
it's far enough that the price could
move up and still fail in that area but
it means that if it goes too far then
it's getting us out before the breakout
continues to happen and therefore we're
cutting our losses early in terms of the
profitable potential outcome
after my decision point at TMP we then
have second order outcomes so one of
these second order outcomes would be a
return to the top of the range and at
that point would be at break even so any
of the move from the decision Point all
the way up to there would still be in
profit and the other second order
outcome would be a break to the bottom
of the range which as I mentioned
earlier we already identified as being
this Zone here so for the probabilities
of these outcomes that would give us a
base rate so the percentages if we had
no Edge of 57% for the negative outcome
and 43% for the positive outcome but
when we consider all of the context
factors that I've just been explaining
to you throughout this video we can make
adjustments to these probabilities which
gives us an end estimated probability of
47% for the negative outcome and 53% for
the positive outcome just based on the
first order outcomes so with these
estimated probabilities we can now
calculate the trade expectancy based on
this formula here so the expectancy for
this opportunity was positive my
probability estimates assume that
regardless of whether this individual
trade ends up being a profit or a loss
if I took this type of opportunity over
and over again it would be profitable
overall due to those probabilities now
based on the first order outcomes alone
the expectancy wasn't far enough above
my margin of error for me to be able to
take the trade but when I consider the
second order outcomes it pushes that
expectancy up even more and makes this a
viable trade opportunity So based on the
expectancy I then choose the position
size which would be relatively low for
this one and it was just 0.7% at risk
now as I mentioned earlier I know all of
this can sound like it's a lot of work
and it's quite complex when it's being
explained in this much detail but really
once you learn these skills it becomes
much more automatic and this whole
process can be done in a matter of
minutes without having to spend that
much mental energy it's just like any
other complex skill it feels like a lot
of work at first and then as you get
better and better it just becomes more
automatic and that's the case here as
well you know a lot of Traders
oversimplify the markets rather than
trying to understand the context and the
logic of the situation but in many cases
this just leads them to trading based on
luck without realizing it whereas the
process that we follow with the dwo
method allows you to measure your skill
level objectively so that we don't rely
on luck and in one of our next videos
I'll show you what I mean with that how
we can measure the skill level
objectively and why this approach that
I'm explaining to you is therefore much
better than just you know following some
set of criteria and hoping for the best
okay so the important question now what
happened next well after entering the
trade the price headed directly to the
first decision point so at this point
there was potential for this to be a
higher low and lead to the next wave
going through the top of the range and
continuing in bullish structure
therefore the stop loss could be dropped
slightly to be based on these highs as
breaking these highs would significantly
change the context and therefore
increase the probability of a negative
move now I have an important rule that I
always try and stick to and I try to
encourage other traders to stick with
this rule as well and the rule is
whenever you reach decision Point
whether you decide to take an action or
you decide that no action is needed you
should always at that point in time know
where your next decision points are
going to be this avoids you being
reactive to every price move that
happens and ensures that you're only
going to make decisions when it's
logical to do so because Traders get too
reactive your emotions get caught up and
you want to bank your profit when you
have it and then you end up seeing the
price run away into more profit and you
could have stayed in it if you made a
more logical decision so the next
decision points at this point in time it
was going to be at the bottom of the
range or obviously breaking back to the
top of the range and we actually reached
the bottom of the range the next day
after some overnight consolidation we
then broke through the Zone but then we
came back through it and tested it from
the other side which meant we had the
path of resistance below the price and
it was also around the point of control
of the value area so since we were so
close to the end of the week at that
point and this wasn't a huge opportunity
with a huge profit built up it made more
sense to be neutral for the weekend to
be out of the trade this is generally
what I like to do with most of my trades
unless it's like a more long-term one
like trades in the other category that
I'll explain to you another time I
prefer to be neutral and not take the
risk of something disruptive happening
on Saturday or Sunday when the markets
are closed and then gapping open for the
start of the next week
so that was a logical exit point for
this trade and if it wasn't for the
weekend it would have made sense to
maybe take a partial profit and leave
the rest open for a continuation of that
bearish structure since that's what the
context was showing us at that time now
if you want to see more trades like this
and to get more insights from me I have
a mailing list that you'll see linked
Below in the description box and I send
trading lessons and insights to over
20,000 Traders each week including my
end of week email which is called
Nicholas notes I know original and in
that email I always share a trade of the
week and this trade that I've just
walked you through was actually in the
previous one so if you want to get
access to all of this you can sign up in
the description box but you also get
access if you sign up for the free
training that I mentioned earlier so you
might as well go and do that anyway then
you get an extra thing there thanks for
watching see you soon